When it comes to something
as life-and-death important
as what to feed ourselves
and our families,
we should rely not on
anecdotes, but on facts.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we feature the strangely
complex art of smoothie making!
As it turns out,
if you make your
smoothies the wrong way
you can partially destroy
valuable phytonutrients.
Here’s our first story.
There are
recommended daily intakes
of essential nutrients
like vitamins
to prevent deficiencies,
but recently the first
dietary recommendation
for a bioactive food compound
was published.
Bioactives are food compounds
that are not necessary
for basic human needs
but may have health benefits;
for example, plant metabolites
called flavonoids.
Flavonoids are
a type of polyphenol,
of which the most commonly
consumed are flavan-3-ols,
also known as just flavanols.
A review of the literature
suggested that the intake
of 400 to 600 mg a day
of flavanols
would be beneficial
for cardiometabolic protection,
potentially helping to improve
blood pressure, cholesterol,
and blood sugars.
Note, it's specified
that these are food guidelines,
not supplement guidelines,
though really,
they're more like
beverage guidelines
as tea—green or black—
would be by far
the easiest way
to reach those levels,
though there are
also certainly some
in a variety
of berries and cocoa.
However, there is an enzyme
called polyphenol oxidase
that can break down polyphenols
like flavanols.
That's what causes certain
fruits and vegetables to brown
when you cut into them,
like bananas and potatoes.
Why would a plant
do that to itself?
Apparently
as a defense mechanism,
part of the plant's
own immune system.
When exposed to oxygen,
polyphenol oxidase
can oxidize polyphenols
into breakdown products
with antimicrobial activity.
So, when a banana gets bruised
or you cut open an avocado,
the polyphenol oxidase
can start oxidizing polyphenols
into defensive compounds
that can glom together
and form a brown compound
called melanin.
The same class of compounds that
darkens the skin of a banana
darkens our skin, too.
Okay, no problem, we can just
not eat brown bananas,
as that's visual evidence
that many of the polyphenols
have been lost.
But what if you mixed
that banana,
which you know is filled with
the polyphenol oxidase enzyme,
into a smoothie
with polyphenol-rich foods,
like berries or cocoa?
Might you end up
with less nutrition?
Big Chocolate-funded researchers
sought to find out.
They put about half a cup (40 g)
of cocoa's worth
of cocoa flavanols into
a smoothie containing banana,
compared to the same amount
in a berry smoothie
with no bananas.
Here's a measure of how many
of the chocolate flavanols
made it into the blood stream
within hours of drinking
the chocolatey berry smoothie,
compared to
the same amount of cocoa
blended into a banana smoothie.
It's almost as if you hardly put
any cocoa in there at all,
presumably because
the banana enzymes chopped up
all the chocolate goodies.
Let's not presume, though.
They blended up the chocolatey
banana smoothie again—
banana, almond milk,
and cocoa flavanols—
and then just measured
the amount of flavanols
as the smoothie sat for an hour.
Check it out.
The cocoa flavanols plummeted,
more than a 90 percent drop,
a half-life of, like,
10 minutes,
so every 10 minutes or so,
the levels drop in half.
How do they know for sure it was
the polyphenol oxidase enzyme?
Because when they added
specific enzyme blockers,
they blocked the effect.
Okay, no problem.
If you're adding bananas
to your smoothies,
can't you just chug it quickly
before the enzyme does its job?
Presumably,
the enzyme would be deactivated
when it hit the acid bath
of the stomach,
but let's not presume.
You don't know
until you put it to the test.
I love that the researchers did
all these extra steps.
This time they made study
participants alternate sips
between a straight
banana-almond milk smoothie
and, like, chocolate milk,
cocoa flavanols
plus almond milk.
So, there was
no premixing in the blender
between the banana enzyme
and the flavanols,
just mixing in the stomach.
Here's how many cocoa flavanols
make it into your bloodstream
when sipping
the chocolate milk alone.
Mixed in the stomach
with banana, and you get this:
37 percent less
in your bloodstream,
which shows that
the banana enzyme can still do
some polyphenol damage
in the stomach.
And, yes, in simulated
stomach acid conditions,
the polyphenol oxidase enzyme
is indeed down but not out.
So yeah, if you drink
a smoothie with banana in it,
it's better to not let it
sit around.
But even if you drink it
immediately,
you may still get
less polyphenols in your system
than if you would have
skipped the banana.
But banana makes smoothies
so rich and creamy.
Anything we can add
to the smoothie
to counter the banana
enzyme's effects?
That's exactly
what I'll cover next.
There is one food that has
more polyphenol oxidase activity
than a banana,
and it's a vegetable
that's not a potato.
What vegetable turns brown
that's not a white potato?
A white mushroom.
White button mushrooms
are packed with that
polyphenol munching enzyme—
even more so than bananas.
Now, for those of you thinking,
don't worry,
I don't expect to be putting
mushrooms in my smoothies
anytime soon,
some people add avocado
to smoothies
or make
a chocolate avocado pudding.
Here's a question:
What if you eat mushrooms
with a meal packed
with polyphenol-rich foods?
Might they mix in your stomach
and decrease the absorption
of the anthocyanins
in red cabbage
or the berries in dessert,
for instance?
You could also imagine
having some potatoes or eggplant
in a meal.
But note,
this is for fresh produce.
The enzyme is destroyed
by cooking.
And remember,
we should be cooking
our white mushrooms anyway
because of the agaritine, right?
So, problem solved.
Who wants to cook their bananas,
though?
What else can we put
in a smoothie?
My favorite is mango,
which you can buy frozen
when it's not in season.
Do we have to worry
about it having
polyphenol-eating enzymes?
Well, what happens
when you cut open a mango?
Does it go brown?
No, so it's probably fine.
And indeed,
when researchers measured
polyphenol oxidase activity
in a bunch
of fruits and vegetables,
mango had 500 times less
than banana.
The apple doesn't surprise me,
since it goes brown so fast,
but what's with the beet greens?
Better to use
something like kale
for your green smoothies
instead,
where enzyme activity
is undetectable.
Should you not add bananas
to your oatmeal?
I no longer add it
to my cran-chocolate pomegranate
breakfast bowl,
since I don't want to lose
any of the polyphenols.
But what if you're not making
something chocolatey?
The study only tested
the effects of the enzyme
on cocoa flavanols.
They didn't check to see
if mixing bananas with berries
would affect
the berry phytonutrients,
but the presumption is
that it would.
And what does this mean
for bottled smoothie drinks
that you buy off the shelf
in the store?
Well, if they've been
pasteurized,
then it should be okay,
since the heat should destroy
the enzyme.
That's why vegetables are
blanched before they're frozen—
to destroy the enzymes.
Even just heating banana
to 70°C (160°F),
which is like
the temperature of hot tea,
for two minutes in the presence
of vitamin C and citric acid
(which might come
from lemon juice)
would suppress the enzyme
by 80 percent.
I'm not suggesting drinking
hot smoothies, but rather that,
depending on the ingredients,
pasteurized smoothie drinks
may not share the same problem
as fresh-made smoothies.
What about just the vitamin C
and citric acid alone,
like putting lemon juice
in your smoothie?
Only cuts the enzyme activity
down by 13 percent.
Works wonders
on a cut apple, though,
slashing enzyme activity
nearly in half,
which explains why lemon juice
can keep your fruit salad
from turning brown.
Anything we can add
to a banana smoothie
to inhibit the enzyme?
Sulfites used to be put
on fresh fruits and vegetables
until they were banned in 1986,
following cases
of sulfite-induced asthma.
They're still used
in dried fruit, though,
to prevent browning.
What about natural agents?
Onion extracts can prevent
the browning of pears.
Both fresh and cooked
onion juice,
but there's got to be a better
option for your smoothie.
Pineapple seems to help keep
apples from browning,
and bananas too,
but that was after
soaking in pineapple juice
for three days,
so it's not clear
if it would work right away.
There was a study comparing
lemon juice and white wine
to prevent browning
in pastry dough.
You've heard of hard cider,
hard seltzer?
The lemon juice beat out
the wine, though,
so better a lemon squeeze
than drinking a hard smoothie.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you see any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest major book,
“How Not to Age” is out.
Check it out from your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books
go to charity.
I actually just came out
with another small book:
an easy 100-page read on
Ozempic and other GLP-1 drugs.
Go to NutritionFacts.org
and click on “Books”
to see where you can get an e-book,
audiobook, or paperback of it.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There are no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.